<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Mind Vortex</title>
    <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io"/>
    <updated>2013-12-24T04:48:04.224Z</updated>
    <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io</id>
    <author>
        <name>Petrik van der Velde</name>
        <email></email>
    </author>

    
        <entry>
            <title>Sherlock configuration - Verification</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-24_Setting-up-Sherlock-verification.html"/>
            <updated>2013-12-24T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-24_Setting-up-Sherlock-verification.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After the configuration of the &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2013-12-10_Setting-up-Sherlock-serverside.html&quot;&gt;host machine&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2013-12-11_Setting-up-Sherlock-virtualmachines.html&quot;&gt;virtual machines&lt;/a&gt; the final step in the configuration of Sherlock is to verify that everything is configured correctly. This can be done by using the verification package that comes with each &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/releases&quot;&gt;release&lt;/a&gt; of Sherlock. In order to use the verification package take the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unpack the &lt;strong&gt;verification.zip&lt;/strong&gt; package to a directory somewhere (e.g. &lt;code&gt;c:\temp\sherlock&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update the configuration file &lt;code&gt;Sherlock.VerificationConfiguration.msbuild&lt;/code&gt; with the following settings:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ConfigurationReportDirectory:&lt;/strong&gt; The directory where you want the final report to be placed. Note that both the user who requests the test and the user which is used to run the Sherlock services need to have access to this directory. The &lt;code&gt;report&lt;/code&gt; directory that was created on the &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2013-12-10_Setting-up-Sherlock-serverside.html&quot;&gt;host&lt;/a&gt; machine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ConfigurationServerUrl:&lt;/strong&gt; The URL of the web service, e.g. &lt;code&gt;http:\\myhostmachine\sherlock.api&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ConfigurationOperatingSystem:&lt;/strong&gt; The operating system name that you want to test with. This needs to match one of the operating systems that has been registered with the management website and which is installed on at least one of your test environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ConfigurationOperatingSystemServicePack:&lt;/strong&gt; Can be left empty if the operating system has no service pack. If the operating system has a service pack then it needs to match the service pack name of the operating system as registered with the management web site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ConfigurationOperatingSystemCulture:&lt;/strong&gt; The &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IETF_language_tag&quot;&gt;culture&lt;/a&gt; as defined for the registered operating system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ConfigurationOperatingSystemPointerSize:&lt;/strong&gt; The &amp;#39;bitness&amp;#39; or pointer size for the operating system, either 32 or 64 bits. Should again match the value that was provided when the operating system was registered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ConfigurationRemotePcWorkingPath:&lt;/strong&gt; A path where the test files will be placed on the test environment, e.g. &lt;code&gt;c:\temp&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ConfigurationSherlockConsoleDirectory:&lt;/strong&gt; The directory where the console application is installed, this may be a UNC path or a normal directory, e.g. &lt;code&gt;\\MyHostMachine\console&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Execute the &lt;code&gt;Sherlock.ExecuteVerificationTests.msbuild&lt;/code&gt; script. This script will prepare the files to be send across (a test application and some test scripts), start the console application, register the test and then wait for the reports to be produced. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the reports will come back with some errors. The verification was designed this way on purpose to make it possible to test the error handling. In the end there should be three reports, one for each known test configuration version, i.e. v1.0, v1.1 and v1.2. The reports should show the following errors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The script execution that executes &lt;code&gt;c:\temp\Sherlock.Verification.Console.exe&lt;/code&gt; with the &lt;code&gt;-f&lt;/code&gt; command line argument. The &lt;code&gt;-f&lt;/code&gt; parameter indicates that the process should &amp;#39;fail&amp;#39; and exit with an exit code of 1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The script execution for &lt;code&gt;c:\temp\Sherlock.Verfication.Console.exe&lt;/code&gt; with parameter &lt;code&gt;-c&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;-c&lt;/code&gt; parameter indicates that the process should exit with an unhandled exception. The exit code for the process should be -532462766.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The application execution &lt;code&gt;c:\temp\Sherlock.Verification.Console.exe&lt;/code&gt; with the &lt;code&gt;-f&lt;/code&gt; command line argument. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The application execution for &lt;code&gt;c:\temp\Sherlock.Verfication.Console.exe&lt;/code&gt; with parameter &lt;code&gt;-c&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;troubleshooting&quot;&gt;Troubleshooting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there are any problems during the verification then the first thing to look at are the debug logs which are written by the different applications. The logs are generally found in &lt;code&gt;c:\ProgramData\Sherlock\&amp;lt;APP_NAME&amp;gt;\&amp;lt;VERSION&amp;gt;\logs&lt;/code&gt;. Notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If there is not enough information in the logs then you can change the log level in the application configuration file under the &lt;code&gt;DefaultLogLevel&lt;/code&gt; configuration option. The available levels are (from most verbose to least verbose):&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trace &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Debug&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Info&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Warn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Error&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fatal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;None&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The applications running in the test environment also log but those logs may be removed if the test environment is a virtual machine. However version 1.2 of the test configuration file has the possibly to copy the logs back to the host machine for inclusion into the test report. For this to work set the &lt;code&gt;includesystemlog&lt;/code&gt; attribute of the &lt;code&gt;includeinreport&lt;/code&gt; element to &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some standard problems that may occur are mentioned below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;console-and-web-service&quot;&gt;Console and web service&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the console application fails to connect to the web service because it cannot find the web service then verify that the web service can be reached. The two main problems that could be the root cause of this are either the web service is not running or the user which started the console application has no access rights to the web service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the console application crashes due to a URL problem (see the log file) then it is most likely that you put a partial URL, e.g. &lt;code&gt;mycoolserver\sherlock.api&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;http://mycoolserver/sherlock.api&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the console successfully manages to go through nearly all the test registration steps but fails on the transfer of the test files then there is quite likely a problem with the web service permissions to write to the &lt;code&gt;App_Data&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the web service fails on the first call then there is quite likely a problem with the database connection. This is most likley either a problem with the connection string or a problem with the permissions. In case of a permission issue check if the user which is running the web service can access the stored procedures in the database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;update-service&quot;&gt;Update service&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the update service is unable to verify the update packages then it is not able to access the public key file. Make sure the configuration file points to the public key file and that this file is reachable by the service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;master-controller&quot;&gt;Master controller&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the master controller fails to connect to the database this could point to either a problem with the connection string or a problem with the permissions. In case of a permissions problem again check that the user running the master controller can access the stored procedures in the database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the master controller is unable to start a virtual machine then the &lt;em&gt;SherlockUser&lt;/em&gt; may not have &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.msdn.com/b/virtual_pc_guy/archive/2008/01/17/allowing-non-administrators-to-control-hyper-v.aspx&quot;&gt;permissions&lt;/a&gt; to start the virtual machines. The log will show this as an error in the environment loading. Probably a security exception.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the controller is blocked by the firewall, or the firewall on the test environment is blocking, then there will be no communication between the test environment and the host. The log shows this through the fact that the host will wait an excessive amount of time for the remote &amp;#39;endpoint&amp;#39; to connect. A normal start up takes around 2 minutes for a test environment start, operating system load and Sherlock load.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>nAnicitus release - V0.1.4.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-22_nAnicitus-Release-V0140.html"/>
            <updated>2013-12-22T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-22_nAnicitus-Release-V0140.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/nAnicitus/releases/tag/V0.1.4.0&quot;&gt;V0.1.4.0&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/nanicitus.html&quot;&gt;nAnicitus&lt;/a&gt; symbol store application has been released. This release fixes issue &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/nAnicitus/issues/1&quot;&gt;#1&lt;/a&gt;. If a package is locked by the operating system, e.g. because the file write has not completed yet, then nAnicitus will try to load the package 3 times, waiting 5 seconds between each try. On top of that if the loading of a package fails then the nAnicitus will retry loading the package 3 times before giving up.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Nuclei release - V0.7.1.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-21_Nuclei-Release-V0710.html"/>
            <updated>2013-12-21T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-21_Nuclei-Release-V0710.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Nuclei/releases/tag/V0.7.1.0&quot;&gt;V0.7.1.0&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/nuclei.html&quot;&gt;Nuclei&lt;/a&gt; library has been released. This release fixes issue &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Nuclei/issues/9&quot;&gt;#9&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Sherlock configuration - Virtual machines</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-11_Setting-up-Sherlock-virtualmachines.html"/>
            <updated>2013-12-11T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-11_Setting-up-Sherlock-virtualmachines.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2013-12-10_Setting-up-Sherlock-serverside.html&quot;&gt;setting up the host machine&lt;/a&gt; the next step in the &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2013-12-04_Regression-testing-with-Sherlock.html&quot;&gt;configuration&lt;/a&gt; of Sherlock is to set up one or more virtual machines. Each virtual machine will have the following applications installed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The update service which handles the installation of the latest available Sherlock binaries. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The executor service which handles the communication with the master controller, handles the download and upload of test files and test reports and controls the test execution. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The application which executes the test steps. This has been separated from the service so that: &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is possible to run the application on the desktop while the executor service is running as a Windows service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any fatal errors in the test application don&amp;#39;t affect the service, thereby maintaining communication with the master controller, and thus allowing error reports to be send.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is possible to run multiple applications under different accounts (planned in future releases).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The configuration process for a virtual machine consists of the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new virtual machine and install the operating system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure the operating system on the virtual machine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install and configure the Sherlock applications on the virtual machine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Store information about the virtual machine in the host database&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;preparing-the-virtual-machine&quot;&gt;Preparing the virtual machine&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step is to create a &lt;a href=&quot;http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc772480.aspx&quot;&gt;new virtual machine&lt;/a&gt; and install the operating system. This should be straight forward but there a few things to look out for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The operating system must (currently) support &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.NET_Framework_version_history#.NET_Framework_4.5&quot;&gt;.NET 4.5&lt;/a&gt; because that is what Sherlock is needs to run on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The network for the virtual machine must be set up so that it can at the very least see the host machine and the other virtual machines stored on the same host machine.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; Windows networks can &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.petri.co.il/working-with-domain-member-virtual-machines-and-snapshots.htm&quot;&gt;deny access&lt;/a&gt; to the test virtual machines after being used for a while (usually 30 days) due to the fact that the test machine is reset after each test, thereby not allowing it to handle the renewal of network identification keys correctly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;preparing-the-operating-system&quot;&gt;Preparing the operating system&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the creation of the virtual machine and the installation of the operating system it is necessary to configure the operating system. Some of the changes are necessary for Sherlock to function while others are necessary only from a test perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets first start with the changes required for Sherlock to function. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If .NET 4.5 is not already installed, then install it. Without it Sherlock won&amp;#39;t run at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new user that will be used to execute the tests. This user needs to be an administrator so that the execution of an MSI install can succeed without the need for elevation (which is &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/5098121/how-can-i-get-elevated-permissions-uac-via-impersonation-under-a-non-interacti&quot;&gt;a bit tricky&lt;/a&gt; from an application). The user can be either a machine local administrator or a domain user  which is granted administration rights on the machine.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note that there might a difference between a domain user with administrative rights on the computer and a local administrator. If you turn UAC off then in general a local administrator is running all applications elevated while the applications started by the domain user run with no elevation only to be silently elevated if requested to do so. Unfortunately this means that the domain user will not be able to run a silent install from a command line unless that command line is explicitly elevated (which is not possible from an application).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disable User Access Control (UAC) so that Sherlock can execute MSI installations. &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; In some cases corporate network controls and/or group policies override local settings. In those cases talk to the local IT people regarding UAC. Also note that on Windows 8 it is not possible to turn off the UAC by moving the &amp;#39;UAC slider&amp;#39; all the way down. This is because Metro applications require some form of UAC to exist in order for them to work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally before installing Sherlock a few tweaks should be made to the operating system configuration so that the automated tests can proceed. Note that for all the following changes there may be group policies in place put there by your local IT service. It may be necessary to talk to the IT people about the settings you want to change and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brianbondy.com/blog/id/100/&quot;&gt;reason&lt;/a&gt; you need to change those settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interactive user:&lt;/strong&gt; If you need to run interactive tests, e.g. UI tests, then you need to make sure a user is logged in. Use &lt;a href=&quot;http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/sysinternals/bb963905.aspx&quot;&gt;Autologon&lt;/a&gt; to automatically log your user in when the computer starts while still maintaining password security.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Windows 8 switch to desktop:&lt;/strong&gt; If you are on Windows 8 you need to make sure that the desktop is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.7tutorials.com/how-boot-desktop-windows-8-skip-start-screen&quot;&gt;available&lt;/a&gt; for interactive applications to execute on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Screen saver:&lt;/strong&gt; In order to prevent any interactive tests from failing due to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://windows.microsoft.com/en-nz/windows-vista/turn-your-screen-saver-on-or-off&quot;&gt;screensaver&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;http://answers.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/forum/windows_7-security/disable-automatic-lock-with-windows-7/daef8f0a-810f-46e8-9420-3c32c4bd6479&quot;&gt;automatic locking of the desktop&lt;/a&gt; both those features need to be turned off. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Windows error reporting:&lt;/strong&gt; Any tests that run on the desktop may hang eternally if the application under tests fails and displays the Windows Error Reporting (WER) dialog. In order to prevent this from happening &lt;a href=&quot;http://4sysops.com/archives/how-to-disable-windows-error-reporting/&quot;&gt;WER should be disabled&lt;/a&gt;. The most efficient way of doing this is to use the group policy controls to disable the following elements:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;code&gt;Computer Configuration\Administrative Templates\System\Internet Communication Management\Internet Communication settings&lt;/code&gt; enable the setting: &lt;code&gt;Turn off Windows Error Reporting&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;code&gt;Computer Configuration\Administrative Templates\Windows Components\Windows Error Reporting&lt;/code&gt; enable the settings &lt;code&gt;Disable Windows error reporting&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Prevent display of the user interface for critical errors&lt;/code&gt;, and disable the setting &lt;code&gt;Display error notification&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automatic updates:&lt;/strong&gt; Automatic updates can be disabled because they will never be deployed due to the fact that the machine is reset after each test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;configuring-sherlock&quot;&gt;Configuring Sherlock&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the operating system is configured &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/releases&quot;&gt;Sherlock&lt;/a&gt; can be installed and configured. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unzip the &lt;strong&gt;service.zip&lt;/strong&gt; package into the &lt;code&gt;c:\sherlock&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copy the XML file containing the public key used to sign the manifests to the virtual machine and place it in the &lt;code&gt;c:\sherlock&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the configuration file (&lt;code&gt;Sherlock.Service.exe.config&lt;/code&gt;) and update the following settings:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ApplicationName:&lt;/strong&gt; The name of the application for which updates should be tracked, in this case that is: &lt;code&gt;Sherlock.Service.Executor.exe&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UpdateManifestUri:&lt;/strong&gt; The URL of the manifest file, in this case: &lt;code&gt;http:\\myhostmachine\appupdate\executorservice.manifest&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ManifestPublicKeyFile:&lt;/strong&gt; The path to the XML file containing the public key section of the manifest signing key, e.g. &lt;code&gt;C:\sherlock\manifestsigningkey.public.xml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set the update service to start automatically when the computer starts. This can be done as an actual service (in case no interactive tests will be executed) or by automatically starting the application when the user logs on to windows (in case interactive tests need to be executed).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The last step is to let the executor controller through the firewall. For this create an inbound rule that allows &lt;code&gt;c:\ProgramData\Sherlock\Sherlock.Service.Executor\{VERSION}\Sherlock.Service.Executor.exe&lt;/code&gt; to connect to all types of protocols. Normally only Domain and private networks should be sufficient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;testing&quot;&gt;Testing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the operating system and Sherlock have been configured it is sensible to test the configurations to make sure it all works. In order to do this take the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restart the virtual machine. Once the machine starts up it should (depending on your configuration)&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatically log on the test user&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On windows 8 switch to the desktop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start the Sherlock update service. The service should download the latest version of the executor controller and start it. You can verify this by looking at the logs which can be found in &lt;code&gt;c:\programdata\sherlock\sherlock.service\{VERSION}\logs&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;c:\programdata\sherlock\sherlock.service.executor\{VERSION}\logs&lt;/code&gt; for the update service and the executor controller respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After both applications have started stop them both by stopping the update service (&lt;code&gt;Sherlock.Service&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once the applications have been stopped remove the data from the directory &lt;code&gt;c:\ProgramData\Sherlock&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shut down the machine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.msdn.com/b/virtual_pc_guy/archive/2008/01/16/managing-snapshots-with-hyper-v.aspx&quot;&gt;snapshot&lt;/a&gt; of the current state of the virtual machine and give it a sensible name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;host-configuration&quot;&gt;Host configuration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally the last step in the configuration of a new test environment is to register the environment with Sherlock through the management website.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Sherlock configuration - Server side</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-10_Setting-up-Sherlock-serverside.html"/>
            <updated>2013-12-10T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-10_Setting-up-Sherlock-serverside.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this post I will explain how to configure the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock&quot;&gt;Sherlock&lt;/a&gt; host services, which handle test registration and selection and control of the test environments for a test. The set-up follows the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparing the host machine which includes installation of the OS and the required services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installation of database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installation of the web parts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creation of the update files and the update manifests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installation of the services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configuration of the firewall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Verification of the configuration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;preparing-the-host-machine&quot;&gt;Preparing the host machine&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step in the configuration of the host services is to prepare the machine from which the Hyper-V service will be running. Note that Sherlock does not require that all services run on this machine but for the purposes of this post I will assume that this is the case. The configuration of the host machine consists of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the host operating system on the machine. Both the machine and the operating system need to &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyper-V#System_requirements_and_specifications&quot;&gt;support Hyper-V&lt;/a&gt;. On top of that for the very least the master controller service has to be installed on the host machine, which means it is not possible to install the core Hyper-V version of Windows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create or associate a user which you will use to run the Sherlock services. It is strongly recommended to not run the Sherlock services as local administrator for security reasons. It is more suitable to provide a separate user to run the services. Note that this user will need permissions to run services, but doesn&amp;#39;t need installation permissions etc. For the remainder of this post lets call this user the &lt;em&gt;SherlockUser&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt; If you have a specific user that is used for your build server then it makes sense to use that user, although that is not required.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the &lt;a href=&quot;http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/hh846766.aspx&quot;&gt;Hyper-V role&lt;/a&gt; on the host machine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grant the &lt;em&gt;SherlockUser&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.msdn.com/b/virtual_pc_guy/archive/2008/01/17/allowing-non-administrators-to-control-hyper-v.aspx&quot;&gt;permissions&lt;/a&gt; to start, stop and reset Hyper-V virtual machines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iis.net/learn/get-started/whats-new-in-iis-8/installing-iis-8-on-windows-server-2012&quot;&gt;IIS role&lt;/a&gt; on the host machine. &lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt; that in theory (i.e. this has not been tested) IIS can be installed on a different machine than the host machine as long as it will be able to reach the database. The IIS install will need to have the following parts installed as a minimum:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ASP .NET 4.5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic authentication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Windows Authentication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Management tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Http logging and tracing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.microsoft.com/web/platform/database.aspx&quot;&gt;MSSQL Express 2012&lt;/a&gt; on the host machine. &lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt; As with IIS it is again possible to install the database on any machine as long as both IIS and the Hyper-V host can connect to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a directory that will hold all the files related to Sherlock, e.g. &lt;code&gt;c:\testing&lt;/code&gt;. In that directory create the following sub-directories:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;appupdate&lt;/code&gt; - Contains the application update files and manifests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;console&lt;/code&gt; - Contains the binary files for the console application which is used by the user to register a test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;service&lt;/code&gt; - Contains the binaries for the windows service that will run the controller application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;web.api&lt;/code&gt; - Contains the binaries for the web service that interacts with the database on test registration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;web.intranet&lt;/code&gt; - Contains the binaries for the management web site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;reports&lt;/code&gt; - The location where tests can place their generated reports. Note that Sherlock allows placing test reports in any location as long as the service has access to that directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;temp&lt;/code&gt; - The temporary directory used for report generation etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share the &lt;code&gt;reports&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;console&lt;/code&gt; directories so that they can be accessed over the network. The &lt;code&gt;console&lt;/code&gt; directory will only need read access, the &lt;code&gt;reports&lt;/code&gt; directory will need read and write access.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/nAdoni&quot;&gt;nAdoni&lt;/a&gt; manifest signing tool. This application will be used sign the update manifest files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generate the update keys by executing the following command line (assuming that you installed nadoni in &lt;code&gt;c:\tools\nadoni&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;pre class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;dos&quot;&gt;c:\tools\nadoni\keygenerator\nadoni.keygenerator.exe --private=&amp;lt;PATH_TO_PRIVATE_KEY_FILE&amp;gt; --public=&amp;lt;PATH_TO_PUBLIC_KEY_FILE&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;PATH_TO_PRIVATE_KEY_FILE&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; points to the XML file that will contain the private and public parts of the manifest signing key and &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;PATH_TO_PUBLIC_KEY_FILE&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; points to the XML file that will contain the public part of the manifest signing key. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;database&quot;&gt;Database&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second step in the installation process is to create the Sherlock database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unpack the &lt;em&gt;sql.zip&lt;/em&gt; file that is part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/releases&quot;&gt;Sherlock release&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create database called &lt;code&gt;Sherlock&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply all the SQL scripts from the &lt;em&gt;sql.zip&lt;/em&gt; file, starting at the V1 script through to the latest upgrade script &lt;em&gt;Sherlock_Upgrade_Vm_To_Vn.sql&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provide permissions for the user that will be connecting to the database. You can either use the &lt;em&gt;SherlockUser&lt;/em&gt; or you can create an SQL user. Grant this user the following access:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;db_datareader&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;db_datawriter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grant access to stored procedures. This can be done via: &lt;code&gt;GRANT EXEC TO &amp;lt;STORED_PROCEDURE_NAME&amp;gt; TO &amp;lt;SQL_USER&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. Given that Sherlock only accesses the database through stored procedures, there is no direct table access, there are quite a few stored procedures which means it makes sense to create a script in order to grant access to the stored procedures. The following SQL script can be used to generate an access script for the user:&lt;pre class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;sql&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;operator&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;SELECT&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'GRANT EXEC ON '&lt;/span&gt;+ SCHEMA_NAME(schema_id) + &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'.'&lt;/span&gt; + name + &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;' TO &amp;lt;SQL_USER&amp;gt;'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; sys.procedures
&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;ORDER&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;BY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set-up a back up for the Sherlock database. &lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt; The test data is only useful to Sherlock and then only when tests are either running or haven&amp;#39;t been run yet. In other words there is no useful information for the user describing test results etc.. However the information describing the available test environments should be backed-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;iis&quot;&gt;IIS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step number three for the installation of Sherlock is to configure the web service, web page and the application update location. We&amp;#39;ll start with the application update location:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In IIS Manager create a new virtual directory under the default web site using the following settings &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alias:&lt;/strong&gt; AppUpdate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Path:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;c:\testing\appupdate&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connect as:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;SherlockUser&lt;/em&gt;. Make sure the &lt;em&gt;SherlockUser&lt;/em&gt; has read permissions for the directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow directory browsing through the &lt;em&gt;IIS -&amp;gt; Directory Browsing&lt;/em&gt; Feature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally test access to this directory via a browser by going to &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;HOST_ADDRESS&amp;gt;\AppUpdate&lt;/code&gt;. This should display the contents of the directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before configuring the web site and the web service create a new application pool with the following settings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name:&lt;/strong&gt; SherlockAppPool&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.NET Framework version:&lt;/strong&gt; V4.0.30319&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managed pipeline mode:&lt;/strong&gt; Integrated &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next project to configure is the web site that will be used to manage the testing environments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unzip &lt;strong&gt;Sherlock.Web.Intranet.sql&lt;/strong&gt; to the &lt;code&gt;c:\testing\web.intranet&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In IIS Manager create a new application under the default web site using the following settings:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alias:&lt;/strong&gt; Sherlock.Intranet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Application pool:&lt;/strong&gt; SherlockAppPool&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Path:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;c:\testing\web.intranet&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connect as:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;SherlockUser&lt;/em&gt;. Again make sure that the &lt;em&gt;SherlockUser&lt;/em&gt; has access to the directory containing the web site binaries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set the authentication for the web site to be anonymous only.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the connection string to be as given below:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;script src='https://gist.github.com/7866267.js'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove the following sections from the configuration file&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System.Web -&amp;gt; Authentication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System.Web -&amp;gt; Authorization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last web project to configure is the web service that will be used to add information about the new tests to the database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unzip &lt;strong&gt;Sherlock.Web.Api.zip&lt;/strong&gt; to the &lt;code&gt;c:\testing\web.api&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In IIS Manager create a new application under the default web site using the following settings:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alias:&lt;/strong&gt; Sherlock.Api&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Application pool:&lt;/strong&gt; SherlockAppPool&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Path:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;c:\testing\web.api&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connect as:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;SherlockUser&lt;/em&gt;. Again make sure that the &lt;em&gt;SherlockUser&lt;/em&gt; has access to the directory containing the web service binaries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the connection string to be the same as given for the management website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set the authentication for the web site to be anonymous only. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;update-manifests-and-files&quot;&gt;Update manifests and files&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two main services for Sherlock, the master controller and the executor controller, are not directly installed on either the host machine or the test environments. The Sherlock service probes the &lt;code&gt;AppUpdate&lt;/code&gt; directory for the binaries of these services. This greatly improves the ease with which Sherlock can be upgraded given that an upgrade of Sherlock does not require any changes to the test environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create the necessary upgrade files for the Sherlock services it will be necessary to update the configuration file of the master controller which takes the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unzip &lt;strong&gt;Service.Master.zip&lt;/strong&gt; into a temporary directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update the configuration file (&lt;code&gt;Sherlock.Service.Master.exe.config&lt;/code&gt;) with the following settings:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TestDataDirectory:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;c:\testing\web.api\App_Data&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TestReportFilesDir:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;c:\testing\temp&lt;/code&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the connection string to be the same as given for the management website. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repackage the binaries into a ZIP archive with the name &lt;strong&gt;Service.Master.zip&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The executor controller does not need any changes to the configuration file and can thus be left untouched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is to create the manifest files that are used by the update service to determine which ZIP archive to use. In order to create the manifests the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/nAdoni&quot;&gt;nAdoni&lt;/a&gt; application is used. This can be done with the following command lines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the master controller:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;dos&quot;&gt;C:\tools\nadoni\manifestbuilder\nAdoni.ManifestBuilder.exe -v=&quot;{VERSION}&quot; -n=&quot;Sherlock.Service.Master.exe&quot; -f=&quot;c:\testing\appupdate\service.master.zip&quot; -u=&quot;http://myhostmachine/appupdate/service.master.zip&quot; -k=&quot;C:\mykeydirectory\manifestsigningkey.private.xml&quot; -o=&quot;c:\testing\appupdate\masterservice.manifest&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for the executor controller:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;dos&quot;&gt;C:\tools\nadoni\manifestbuilder\nAdoni.ManifestBuilder.exe -v=&quot;{VERSION}&quot; -n=&quot;Sherlock.Service.Executor.exe&quot; -f=&quot;c:\testing\appupdate\service.executor.zip&quot; -u=&quot;http://myhostmachine/appupdate/service.executor.zip&quot; -k=&quot;C:\mykeydirectory\manifestsigningkey.private.xml&quot; -o=&quot;c:\testing\appupdate\executorservice.manifest&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to create the manifest files is through the use of the following Msbuild script: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src='https://gist.github.com/6521946.js'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case the following changes must be made to the file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;${PATH_TO_NADONI_DIRECTORY}$&lt;/code&gt; - The path to the directory in which the nAdoni binaries have been placed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;${URL_TO_APP_UPDATE}$&lt;/code&gt; - The URL to the &lt;code&gt;AppUpdate&lt;/code&gt; directory, e.g. &lt;code&gt;http://myhostmachine/appupdate&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;${MANIFEST_SIGNING_KEY_PATH}$&lt;/code&gt; - The path to the XML file that contains the private key information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the following properties must be specified on the command line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Version:&lt;/strong&gt; The version of Sherlock for which the manifest files are generated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;services&quot;&gt;Services&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally on the host machine two applications need to be configured. These are the console application that will be executed by the user to register a test and the update service that will control the master controller application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To configure the console application take the following steps:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unzip the &lt;strong&gt;console.zip&lt;/strong&gt; package into the &lt;code&gt;c:\testing\console&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the configuration file (&lt;code&gt;Sherlock.Console.exe.config&lt;/code&gt;) and update the following settings:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WebServiceUrl:&lt;/strong&gt; Point this to the &lt;em&gt;Sherlock.Api&lt;/em&gt; site, e.g. &lt;code&gt;http://myhostmachine/sherlock.api&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note that the console needs to be accessed from other machines, e.g.from the build server, so make sure that the directory is shared with read-rights for all users that will need access. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To configure the update service take the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unzip the &lt;strong&gt;service.zip&lt;/strong&gt; package into the &lt;code&gt;c:\testing\service&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the configuration file (&lt;code&gt;Sherlock.Service.exe.config&lt;/code&gt;) and update the following settings:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ApplicationName:&lt;/strong&gt; The name of the application for which updates should be tracked, in this case that is: &lt;code&gt;Sherlock.Service.Master.exe&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UpdateManifestUri:&lt;/strong&gt; The URL of the manifest file, in this case: &lt;code&gt;http:\\myhostmachine\appupdate\masterservice.manifest&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ManifestPublicKeyFile:&lt;/strong&gt; The path to the XML file containing the public key section of the manifest signing key, e.g. &lt;code&gt;C:\mykeydirectory\manifestsigningkey.public.xml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install the application as a service by opening an elevated command line and navigating to the &lt;code&gt;c:\testing\service&lt;/code&gt; directory. Then execute the following command line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;brainfuck&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;sherlock&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;service&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;exe&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;install&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;literal&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;username:SherlockUser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;literal&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;password:SherlockPassword&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;literal&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;literal&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;delayed&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;literal&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;servicename:Sherlock&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to the Windows services control and start the service. After a short while this will grab the latest version of the master controller binaries, drop them in &lt;code&gt;C:\ProgramData\Sherlock\Sherlock.Service.Master&lt;/code&gt; and then start the master controller application. You can verify that all is well by checking the log files which are located in &lt;code&gt;C:\ProgramData\Sherlock\Sherlock.Service\{VERSION}\logs&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;C:\ProgramData\Sherlock\Sherlock.Service.Master\{VERSION}\logs&lt;/code&gt; for the service and the master controller respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;firewall&quot;&gt;Firewall&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last step is to let the master controller through the firewall. For this create an inbound rule that allows &lt;code&gt;Sherlock.Service.Master.exe&lt;/code&gt; to connect to all types of protocols. Normally only Domain and private networks should be sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with all that done the host machine configuration is completed.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>PG2 - Top landings?</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-05_PG2-Top-landings.html"/>
            <updated>2013-12-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-05_PG2-Top-landings.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago the weather was once again favourable to learn more new skills on my way to my &lt;a href=&quot;/tags/PG2.html&quot;&gt;PG2 license&lt;/a&gt;. When we arrived at Maioro the wind was just enough to soar. Given that the forecast has indicated an increase in wind strength over the afternoon we decided to practise some ground handling first. After about an hour of practising reverse launches and keeping the glider stable above our heads it was time to fly. The wind was still a bit light but with a lot of scratching I still managed to get 40 - 45 minutes of flying in on my first flight, my longest flight until then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the afternoon progressed the wind strength slowly increased and staying up became easier which resulted in another 45 minute flight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in the afternoon the instructor told me it was possible to get a set of short flights with some top landings in. For my first try I launched, gained some height and then turned in for the top landing and completely stuffed it up. As I started moving over to the landing spot everything accelerated and I tried to slow down and turn at the same time, which meant I was not actually doing either of those things so when I got close to the ground I was still moving at a decent speed and hence I face planted. Fortunately there was no actual damage to either me or the glider.
After recovering from the jitters for a bit I had a second attempt at top landing which took a lot longer to set up and decent but ended in a perfect touch down. The conclusion of all of this is that I need to focus more on flying the glider till the last minute, stay in the harness to maintain the weight shift and focus on the direction of flight more. Oh so much more to learn. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fifth and final flight of the day was flying back to the car park which was quite easy as I only had to fly along the ridges to maintain more than enough height to get to the car park.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Regression testing with Sherlock</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-04_Regression-testing-with-Sherlock.html"/>
            <updated>2013-12-04T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-04_Regression-testing-with-Sherlock.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over a series of posts I hope to explain how to set up and use the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/sherlock.html&quot;&gt;Sherlock&lt;/a&gt; test environment system. The idea is to follow the set up procedure I used both at home for the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/apollo.html&quot;&gt;Apollo&lt;/a&gt; project and the proof of concept I am working on at my work place. But first lets start with a short explanation of what Sherlock is and what it does. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-sherlock&quot;&gt;What is Sherlock&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sherlock consists of a set of applications and services that provide test environment organisation and automatic execution of a set of tests on one or more test environments. The organisation part consists of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keeping track of which environments exist, which are available for testing and which are not, e.g. for maintenance reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What operating system is loaded onto each environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which applications are pre-loaded onto each environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relationships between virtual machines and their (physical) host machine. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The test execution part consists of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Selection of the most suitable environment for a test based on the desired combination of operating system and available applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparing of the environment for test. This includes loading test environments, i.e. waking up physical test environments through the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wake-on-LAN&quot;&gt;Wake-on-LAN&lt;/a&gt; approach and starting virtual machines, and sending over the test data, e.g. installer files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Triggering test execution on the active test environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Processing test status and test report information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post test environment clean-up. This currently only includes resetting virtual machine disks back to the pre-test state.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accumulation of test events and generation of the final test report.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general the Sherlock system will consist of at least one &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyper-V&quot;&gt;Hyper-V&lt;/a&gt; host machine and a set of one or more Hyper-V virtual machines. In this arrangement the host machine handles the test organisation and part of the test execution, while the virtual machines serve as test environments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is possible for Sherlock to execute tests on physical machines it is advised to only execute on virtual machines because of the inability to reset a physical machine back to the pre-test state. Virtual machines on the other hand can easily be restored to the pre-test state through the use of snapshots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-life-of-a-test&quot;&gt;The life of a test&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When executing a test with Sherlock the following steps are present: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The user creates a test configuration file which describes all requirements for the test environment, which steps should be executed and where the report should be placed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The user registers the test with Sherlock via the console application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some time after the registration of the test completed the Sherlock host service loads test information and selects one or more suitable environments to execute the test steps on. The time between the completion of the test registration and the starting of the test execution depends on whether suitable test environments are available and how busy they are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The selected test environments are prepared for the test execution. This preparation includes activating the environment and transferring the test data for each environment (e.g. installer files etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each environment executes the desired test steps and reports back on the success or failure of each test step.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once an environment has completed its test steps it will report the completion the test, upon which the host service will terminate the environment and restore it to the original state.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once all environments have completed their test steps the test is marked as completed and the test report is compiled and placed in the predetermined location.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;pre-requisites&quot;&gt;Pre-requisites&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first pre-requisite in the configuration is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/releases&quot;&gt;latest release&lt;/a&gt; of sherlock. A release consists of a number of ZIP packages including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;console.zip&lt;/strong&gt; - Contains the binaries and configuration files for the console application which is used to register a test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sherlock.web.api.zip&lt;/strong&gt; - The web service that will store information about a new test in the database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sherlock.web.intranet.zip&lt;/strong&gt; - The management web site that can be used to add or remove test environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;service.zip&lt;/strong&gt; - The windows service that is used to run the &lt;em&gt;master controller&lt;/em&gt; or the &lt;em&gt;executor controller&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;service.master.zip&lt;/strong&gt; - The master controller application which handles the scheduling of tests, loading and unloading of test environments and processing of the test reports. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;service.executor.zip&lt;/strong&gt; - The executor controller application which controls the execution of a test on a test environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sql.zip&lt;/strong&gt; - The SQL change scripts for the database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second pre-requisite is the availability of a physical machine on which a Windows version with &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyper-V#System_requirements_and_specifications&quot;&gt;Hyper-V&lt;/a&gt; can be installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;planned-posts-&quot;&gt;Planned posts:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next following posts will describe:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2013-12-10_Setting-up-Sherlock-serverside.html&quot;&gt;How to set up the Hyper-V host machine.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2013-12-11_Setting-up-Sherlock-virtualmachines.html&quot;&gt;How to prepare a virtual machine for use as a testing environment.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2014-12-31_Setting-up-Sherlock-verification.html&quot;&gt;How to verify that all the environments have been configured correctly.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to integrate with a build server. This will discuss build jobs, build scripts and test configuration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A description on how I used Sherlock to perform integration tests on the console application of Apollo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And a description on how I used Sherlock to perform integration tests on a WPF application of &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/apollo.html&quot;&gt;Apollo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Nuclei release - V0.7.0.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-04_Nuclei-Release-V0700.html"/>
            <updated>2013-12-04T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-04_Nuclei-Release-V0700.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Nuclei/releases/tag/V0.7.0.0&quot;&gt;V0.7.0.0&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/nuclei.html&quot;&gt;Nuclei&lt;/a&gt; library has been released. This release adds support for grouping timing results based on their logical area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;cs&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; group1 = &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; TimingGroup(); 
&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;using&lt;/span&gt; (Profiler.Measure(group1, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;My first timing group&quot;&lt;/span&gt;))
{
    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; group2 = &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; TimingGroup();
    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;using&lt;/span&gt; (Profiler.Measure(
        group2, 
        &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;This timing is not a child of the first one&quot;&lt;/span&gt;))
    {
        &lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;// Do stuff here ...&lt;/span&gt;
    }

    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;using&lt;/span&gt; (Profiler.Measure(
        group1, 
        &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;This timing is a child of the first one&quot;&lt;/span&gt;))
    {
        &lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;// Do stuff here ...&lt;/span&gt;
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Setting up nAnicitus</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-03_Setting-up-nAnicitus.html"/>
            <updated>2013-12-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-12-03_Setting-up-nAnicitus.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this post I will explain how to install and configure the nAnicitus windows service. nAnicitus is a windows service that acts as a gatekeeper for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/hardware/ff558848(v=vs.85).aspx&quot;&gt;SymStore&lt;/a&gt; application. SymStore provides a relatively simple way to create a local / private &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/ms680693%28v=vs.85%29.aspx&quot;&gt;symbol server&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This statement should bring up a few questions, cunning questions like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why would a development team even need a symbol server?&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The PDB files which are produced as the result of a build are just as unique as assemblies or executables. Each assembly has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wintellect.com/blogs/jrobbins/pdb-files-what-every-developer-must-know&quot;&gt;one specific PDB&lt;/a&gt; file to which it is linked via a GUID. Each time an assembly is build a new GUID is embedded, even if the source code has not changed. This means that in order to debug a given assembly for which you don&amp;#39;t have the source code, which can happen if you debug other peoples libraries or if you are debugging a crash dump, then you will need the linked PDB file. Hence in order to enable debugging of releases one has to either place the PDB in the same location as the binaries or one has to store the PDB files in a symbol server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why would a development team not use SymStore directly?&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The disadvantage of SymStore is that it is not capable of processing &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/hardware/ff558851(v=vs.85).aspx&quot;&gt;multiple PDB files at the same time&lt;/a&gt;, i.e. it should really only be called by one user at the time. By providing a windows service that synchronizes the access to the SymStore application it is possible for multiple users to add symbols to the symbol server without having to worry about the integrity of the symbol server files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we continue with the installation of nAnicitus lets have a quick look at how nAnicitus works. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The user creates a &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.nuget.org/docs/creating-packages/creating-and-publishing-a-symbol-package&quot;&gt;NuGet symbol package&lt;/a&gt; and places that in a pre-configured upload directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nAnicitus unpacks the symbol package and extracts the PDB files and the source files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For each PDB file it is determined which source files were used to create it. Based on that information a &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/ms680641%28v=vs.85%29.aspx&quot;&gt;symbol stream&lt;/a&gt; is created and inserted into the PDB file which points to the source server path for the source files belonging to the PDB file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The PDB files are uploaded via &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/hardware/ff558848(v=vs.85).aspx&quot;&gt;SymStore&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The source files are uploaded to the source server path.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before installing nAnicitus it is necessary to install the &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/hardware/gg463009.aspx&quot;&gt;debugging tools for windows&lt;/a&gt;. Make sure to install the complete set of tools so that you get all the symbol server tools as well. Once the the debugging tools are installed you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/nAnicitus/releases&quot;&gt;download&lt;/a&gt; and unzip the latest version of nAnicitus. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is to update the configuration file with the directory and UNC paths:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DebuggingToolsDirectory:&lt;/strong&gt; The debugging tools directory (e.g. &lt;code&gt;c:\Program Files (x86)\Windows Kits\8.0\Debuggers\x64&lt;/code&gt;). This path may be left out if it is in the default location (as given here).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SourceIndexUncPath:&lt;/strong&gt; The UNC path to the directory where the indexed sources will be placed (e.g. &lt;code&gt;\\MyServer\sources&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SymbolsIndexUncPath:&lt;/strong&gt; The UNC path to the directory where the indexed symbols (i.e. PDBs) will be placed (e.g. &lt;code&gt;\\MyServer\symbols&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ProcessedPackagesPath:&lt;/strong&gt; The directory where the NuGet symbol packages will be dropped after they are processed. The NuGet symbol packages are saved in this directory so that it is possible to reprocess the packages if for instance the location of the source path changes, e.g. after switching to a new server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UploadPath:&lt;/strong&gt; The directory where the NuGet symbol packages are placed for nAnicitus to process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally to install the application as a windows service, open a command line window with administrative permissions, navigate to the nAnicitus install directory and execute the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;profile&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;filename&quot;&gt;Nanicitus.Service install&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the service is installed use the normal windows services control to change the properties of the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now you should have a working symbol server! &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>PG2 - Bumpy air, smooth air</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-11-19_PG2-Bumpy-air-smooth-air.html"/>
            <updated>2013-11-19T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-11-19_PG2-Bumpy-air-smooth-air.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Once more the &lt;a href=&quot;/tags/PG2.html&quot;&gt;PG2&lt;/a&gt; group gathered for some flying over the weekend. The action this time was at Maioro with a southerly wind providing for a very bumpy ride. Because of the angle between the wind and the cliff the lift band was very narrow and so one had to work hard to stay in the air. Over the course of the day I managed to get three long flights in but unfortunately I only managed to top land one of them, on the other two I bombed out and had to do a decent bit of walking to get back to the start place. Overall it was a good learning experience flying in very bumpy air with not much lift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a little treat for myself I had taken the Monday off from work so that I could go flying if the weather proved to be suitable. The weather forecast for Monday showed great promise for some good flying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convergence_zone&quot;&gt;convergence&lt;/a&gt; hanging around over the city so our instructor decided that with some luck the wind would turn northerly which would make &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Head,_New_Zealand&quot;&gt;North head&lt;/a&gt; an excellent place to fly. After some para-waiting the weather gods decided that the southerly wind would break through the convergence which thereby ended our hopes for flying at North head. Fortunately there are quite a few places around Auckland where flying is possible so our instructor suggested going to &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muriwai&quot;&gt;Maori bay&lt;/a&gt;. When we got to Maori bay it turned out that the wind was smooth and from a suitable direction, so indeed the site was flyable. My first flight was a tandem flight with my instructor. While flying he showed me how to pick the right soaring lines and what to look out for. In the 30 or so minutes that we flew the tandem I learned heaps, and I did most of the flying, except for the start and the landing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the tandem flight I managed to get two shorter flights in with my own glider. The launches were a bit more tricky than I was used to because the start place was on angled ground with the wind coming in slightly off angle. However I managed to get the glider to launch without too much trouble in both situations and I did some amazing flying in yet another beautiful New Zealand beach location.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>nAdoni release - V0.2.1.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-11-13_NAdoni-Release-V0210.html"/>
            <updated>2013-11-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-11-13_NAdoni-Release-V0210.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my haste to release the new &lt;a href=&quot;2013-11-13_NAdoni-Release-V0200.html&quot;&gt;KeyGenerator&lt;/a&gt; functionality I completely forgot to add the packaging of said KeyGenerator. Hence I hereby present Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/nAdoni/releases/tag/V0.2.1.0&quot;&gt;V0.2.1.0&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/nadoni.html&quot;&gt;nAdoni&lt;/a&gt; update manifest builder project which adds the ZIP archive containing the &lt;code&gt;nAdoni.KeyGenerator&lt;/code&gt; console application.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>nAdoni release - V0.2.0.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-11-13_NAdoni-Release-V0200.html"/>
            <updated>2013-11-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-11-13_NAdoni-Release-V0200.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/nAdoni/releases/tag/V0.2.0.0&quot;&gt;V0.2.0.0&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/nadoni.html&quot;&gt;nAdoni&lt;/a&gt; update manifest builder project has been released. This release adds the &lt;code&gt;nAdoni.KeyGenerator&lt;/code&gt; console application to the project. This application can be used to generate the RSA key files which are necessary in order to build the manifest files.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>PG2 - Up and down the coast</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-11-11_PG2-Up-and-down-the-coast.html"/>
            <updated>2013-11-11T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-11-11_PG2-Up-and-down-the-coast.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last weekend once again the wind was suitable for flying at &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kariotahi_Beach&quot;&gt;Kario&lt;/a&gt; and so more flying was had. The weather forecast indicated that the wind was going to be pretty strong and as we arrived on the beach that was confirmed by the general feel and the wind socks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing I had to deal with was the fact that launching was tricky due to the strong winds. The first launch went off without problems but on the second one I got picked up as the glider rose above my head, causing me to fall on my back (yay for back protectors) and the glider to overshoot and collapse. The conclusion was too much brake and not enough moving towards the glider.
At that point Eva taught me how to do sideways launch where you lay the glider out at an angle to the wind, pull one end up first and then use brake on the high side to stabilize the glider above your head. Using this method the glider generates less pull and is relatively easy to control during the launching phase. Unlike the reverse launch however you need to be much more aggressive in pulling up the glider because if you are not, you give the low side time to catch up which defeats the entire purpose of using this method. In fact you want the whole thing to come up on an angle so that you can control the inflation speed.
It took me several attempts at getting the sideways launch right but in the end I got the hang of it well enough to start using them as my launch technique for the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the wind was so strong it was easy to get up high it was possible for me to practise big ears again without having to worry about being forced to land. I also got to try a 360 degree turn which looks strange as you look at the ground track because while you are turning through 360 degrees, the ground track is making a rather deformed curl shape. At the end of the turn it even feels like you snap into place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally at the end of the day we flew back to the car park from the launch site, a flight of about 6 or so kilometres. All in all once again a good days flying.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>nAnicitus release - V0.1.3.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-31_nAnicitus-Release-V0130.html"/>
            <updated>2013-10-31T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-31_nAnicitus-Release-V0130.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/nAnicitus/releases/tag/V0.1.3.0&quot;&gt;V0.1.3.0&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/nanicitus.html&quot;&gt;nAnicitus&lt;/a&gt; symbol store application has been released. This release adds additional logging and improves the handling of unexpected situations during processing of symbol packages.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Sherlock release - V0.4.7.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-30_Sherlock-Release-V0470.html"/>
            <updated>2013-10-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-30_Sherlock-Release-V0470.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/releases/tag/v0.4.7.0&quot;&gt;V0.4.7.0&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/sherlock.html&quot;&gt;Sherlock&lt;/a&gt; regression testing application has been released. This release provides one bug fix:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Windows job object created by the Sherlock service to ensure termination of the Sherlock.Service.Master and Sherlock.Service.Executor applications is now set to only include direct children (i.e. Sherlock.Service.Master / Sherlock.Service.Executor) in the job and not the indirect children. This allows the application under test to create its own job objects even on Windows 7 (which does not allow nesting of job objects) (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/issues/11&quot;&gt;issue #11&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Weekend at Waipapa - Drying tomatoes</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-28_Weekend-at-Waipapa-drying-tomatoes.html"/>
            <updated>2013-10-28T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-28_Weekend-at-Waipapa-drying-tomatoes.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Labour_Day#New_Zealand&quot;&gt;long weekend&lt;/a&gt; my friend Chris organised a climbing trip to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.freeclimb.co.nz/wharepapa.html&quot;&gt;lake Waipapa&lt;/a&gt;, a climbing area with many delicate slab climbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spend both days at the main wall working on some of the climbs. For Chris his climb of the weekend was &amp;#39;Millennium madness&amp;#39;, an amazing corner &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traditional_climbing&quot;&gt;trad&lt;/a&gt; climb which is rated &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grade_%28climbing%29#Ewbank&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;. From the trad gear side you have to make sure that your rack has several finger size pieces of gear so that you can use some at the start of the climb and some near the middle. The crux of the climb is the first 5 or so meters where you have to figure out how to switch between the different foot placements that are available. The climber starts out bridging between a set of small ledges and then transitions to using the crack to foot-jam and then to using some small indentations on the main face. The tricky bit is getting the transition between the different types of foot placements correct. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On saturday Chris had two attempts at cleaning &amp;#39;Millennium Madness&amp;#39; but didn&amp;#39;t quite get it right. It seems that the first time climbing in Waipapa after winter is always tricky as you are trying to re-acquire the correct climbing techniques for the delicate Waipapa climbs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me the plan was to work my long time project called &amp;#39;Sun dried tomatoes&amp;#39;, a delicate &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sport_climbing&quot;&gt;sport&lt;/a&gt; 22. For this climb the main focus is balance and once again foot placements, however unlike &amp;#39;Millennium madness&amp;#39; where there are many features that can serve as hand holds, &amp;#39;sun dried tomatoes&amp;#39; has sections where hand holds are very sparse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last two years or so I&amp;#39;ve semi-seriously tried this climb a bunch of times but until this weekend I never found the motivation to put a continuous focus on the climb. During both days I put a top-rope on the climb and worked the moves a number of times. This helped me figure out where the correct foot placements were, where the clipping holds were and in which locations a rest would be possible. In the end I climbed it on top rope four times, eventually working out the moves. And each day I ended the day with a lead attempt. On Saturday I failed to clean it because my head space wasn&amp;#39;t in the right spot, however on Sunday I managed to push through the hard bits and got to the top clean. So that&amp;#39;s another tick in the books and another sweet climb done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On to other projects it is now ...&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>PG2 - At the top of the stack</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-25_PG2-At-the-top-of-the-stack.html"/>
            <updated>2013-10-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-25_PG2-At-the-top-of-the-stack.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I thought I could repeat the &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2013-10-13_PG2-Spending-a-weekend-in-the-air.html&quot;&gt;full weekend flying&lt;/a&gt; trick that I pulled a few weeks back. The weather forecast was for sunny and windy, but not too windy. So on Saturday morning we drove out to the beach but when we got to the launch site it became clear that it would be touch-and-go due to the high winds. In the end I only got a little hop while practising my launches. After that I practised my ground handling with a &lt;a href=&quot;http://gingliders.com/speedflying/speedriding-gliders/nano/&quot;&gt;Gin Nano&lt;/a&gt; which is a fun little glider but it did feel more like a kite than a real glider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day was a different story. The wind died down just enough and the sun stayed, all in all a perfect day for flying. Because there were a large number of people the group was split into two, the absolute beginners and the people who had flown before. The latter group immediately set up for their first flights while the former group started with ground handling exercises. I was with the group of people who got to prepare for their first flights immediately. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the day I managed to get three flights in, all with varying levels of success. On the first flight of the day I too rushed and stuffed several things up. First of all I was too enthusiastic with the initial launch which lead to the glider pulling me off my feet and then over flying me. We both ended lying on the ground. Fortunately only my ego was damaged so another attempt was made. On the second start I was more controlled but still kinda jittery during the launch and the run. To top it off I managed to twist the brake line around the rises. So in the end I just fly a circuit down to the ground and landed. No harm done and lots of lessons learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second flight was a lot better, much more controlled, although my launch still needs work. I&amp;#39;m not checking the canopy before commencing my launch run and during the run I need to remember to have no pressure on the brakes. During the flight I practised using the speed bar, which is a lot harder to push than I thought, and flying with big ears and speed bar. Turns out on the Atlas the big ears go in very easily (make sure you are really only pulling the outer A&amp;#39;s) but it takes a bit of time for them to come out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the first two flights provided plenty of good (and safe) learning moments, neither flight was very special. However the third flight was one of those magic flights. After checking that the airspace was empty I started my launch, which went smoothly, but then somebody flew too close to the start place for me to continue. The instructor told me to keep my position with the glider above my head while the other paraglider flew by, but my limited skill was no match for the strong desire of my glider to fly and slowly we drifted towards the end of the cliff. A little bit of left brake allowed me to fly away from the other paraglider and then the soaring started. The Atlas climbs and climbs and keeps climbing, going higher and higher. Eventually, mostly thanks to the amazing Atlas, I ended up at the top of the stack looking down onto the start field with its tiny people, a whole bunch of other gliders and looking over the hills to the neighbouring towns. Later on I determined, from looking at the height topo&amp;#39;s online, that I must have been somewhere between 100m and 120m above the beach! That to me was a magic moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately all magic moments must end, otherwise they wouldn&amp;#39;t be magic anymore, and in this case it was ended by my instructor who thought it would be wise for me to come down while the wind was still behaving so on with the big ears and the speed bar and down I went.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Sherlock release - V0.4.6.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-24_Sherlock-Release-V0460.html"/>
            <updated>2013-10-24T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-24_Sherlock-Release-V0460.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/releases/tag/v0.4.6.0&quot;&gt;V0.4.6.0&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/sherlock.html&quot;&gt;Sherlock&lt;/a&gt; regression testing application has been released. This release provides two bug fixes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The MSI installer now verifies that all directories exist before writing to them (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/issues/9&quot;&gt;issue #9&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The X-copy installer now verifies that the destination directory exists before copying files to it (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/issues/10&quot;&gt;issue #10&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Nuclei release - V0.6.7.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-23_Nuclei-Release-V0670.html"/>
            <updated>2013-10-23T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-23_Nuclei-Release-V0670.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Nuclei/releases/tag/V0.6.7.0&quot;&gt;V0.6.7.0&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/nuclei.html&quot;&gt;Nuclei&lt;/a&gt; library has been released. This release fixes a bug in the processing of &lt;code&gt;ICommandSet&lt;/code&gt; return tasks which caused the processor to throw an exception if the return task was a &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ee372288.aspx&quot;&gt;continuation task&lt;/a&gt;. This bug fix means it is now possible to chain tasks and return the final task from an &lt;code&gt;ICommandSet&lt;/code&gt; object. An example of this behaviour is given in the following section of code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;cs&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;interface&lt;/span&gt; IMyCommandSet : ICommandSet
{
    Task DoSomethingAwesome();
}

&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;sealed&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; MyCommand : IMyCommandSet
{
    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; Task DoSomethingAwesome()
    {
        &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; firstTask = Task.Factory.StartNew(
            () =&amp;gt; Thread.Sleep(&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;));
        &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; secondTask = firstTask.ContinueWith(
            t =&amp;gt; Console.WriteLine(&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;Awesome sauce&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)); 
        &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; secondTask
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Sherlock release - V0.4.5.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-23_Sherlock-Release-V0450.html"/>
            <updated>2013-10-23T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-23_Sherlock-Release-V0450.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/releases/tag/v0.4.5.0&quot;&gt;V0.4.5.0&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/sherlock.html&quot;&gt;Sherlock&lt;/a&gt; regression testing application has been released. This release provides one improvement and one bug fix:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The test report can now include files generated during the test (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/issues/5&quot;&gt;issue #5&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sherlock.Service no longer includes a manifest signing key, instead the key is obtained via a configuration setting (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/issues/8&quot;&gt;issue #8&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>PG2 - Spending a weekend in the air</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-13_PG2-Spending-a-weekend-in-the-air.html"/>
            <updated>2013-10-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-13_PG2-Spending-a-weekend-in-the-air.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last weekend another episode in my &lt;a href=&quot;/tags/PG2.html&quot;&gt;PG2 course&lt;/a&gt; took place with flights happening on both Saturday &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; Sunday. Both days started with an off shore breeze but as the day progressed the sea breeze brought six to seven knots of wind from the South-West and we were good to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time we flew from the high launch at at &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kariotahi_Beach&quot;&gt;Kariotahi&lt;/a&gt; which has the lowest point of the launch at about 90m above the beach. The walk up follows a narrow, relatively steep, sandy and muddy path which increased everybody&amp;#39;s desire to top land. Fortunately for us our excellent instructor always managed to get us into a position where top landings were possible, in spite of the sometimes lacking wind strength. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&quot;left&quot; alt=&quot;Cruising around on my Gin Atlas&quot; src=&quot;/images/paragliding/paraglide_0006.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main learning point for this weekend was the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paragliding#Reverse_launch&quot;&gt;reverse launch&lt;/a&gt;. The technique I am being taught has, in some places, been called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://sydneyparagliding.com/flying-techniques/the-effortless-reverse-launch-technique/&quot;&gt;Mitsos reverse launch&lt;/a&gt;. The reverse launch method provides a lot more control over the glider while it is on the ground than the forward launch method, not in the least because one can actually see what the glider is doing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me the hardest part of the reverse launch method so far is controlling the glider as it rises above my head. The launch will go well as long as the glider rises evenly, but as soon as it slides to the right or left side it is hard to get it back to the middle. The second area to focus on is coordinating the turn and the drive when actually launching. Normally I can execute the turn without too much trouble but I don&amp;#39;t always drive correctly so a lot more practise is in order. Fortunately the instructors have given me an old harness and an old glider that I can use to practise my ground handling on days that we&amp;#39;re not flying. In fact I would be doing that right now if there wasn&amp;#39;t a near gale force wind outside ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the two days I managed to do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Six flights of differing lengths with one flight of 30 minutes and others between five and ten minutes long.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Four top landings and two landings near the car park. In all cases the instructor guided me on my landing spot selection and approach paths.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One forwards launch and five reverse launches which all went well except for one reverse launch where I bounced up and down due to a lacking acceleration run.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally I have to say that the Gin Atlas is an amazing glider. I am by no means a good pilot, after all I&amp;#39;m just learning to fly but the Atlas consistently lets me fly higher than nearly all other gliders, save for some of the super high performance gliders. During the weekend all the other gliders had to, at one point or another, work quite hard to stay at the height of the launch site, or even to scratch their way back up to the launch height. The Atlas just only dropped down to the height of the launch a few times, and each time it did a minor puff of wind allowed it to gain more than sufficient height again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Nuclei release - V0.6.6.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-12_Nuclei-Release-V0660.html"/>
            <updated>2013-10-12T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-10-12_Nuclei-Release-V0660.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Nuclei/releases/tag/V0.6.6.0&quot;&gt;V0.6.6.0&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/nuclei.html&quot;&gt;Nuclei&lt;/a&gt; library has been released. This release adds the ability to specify the name and version of the application in the log file. If no application name or version is specified then the information from &lt;code&gt;Assembly.GetEntryAssembly()&lt;/code&gt; is used. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application name and version can be specified when creating a new logger via the &lt;code&gt;LoggerBuilder&lt;/code&gt; like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;cs&quot;&gt;IConfiguration configuration = &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; MyConfiguration();
&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; logger = LoggerBuilder.ForFile(
    &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;@&quot;c:\mylogfile.txt&quot;&lt;/span&gt;,
    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; DebugLogTemplate(configuration, () =&amp;gt; DateTimeOffset.Now),
    applicationName,
    applicationVersion);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Nuclei release - V0.6.5.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-26_Nuclei-Release-v0650.html"/>
            <updated>2013-09-26T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-26_Nuclei-Release-v0650.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Nuclei/releases/tag/V0.6.5.0&quot;&gt;V0.6.5.0&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/nuclei.html&quot;&gt;Nuclei&lt;/a&gt; library has been released. This release adds an option to allow the user to select which
types of channels the communication layer is allowed to use. The communication layer can be allowed to use TCP/IP channels, named pipe channels or both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous versions in the constructor of the &lt;code&gt;CommunicationModule&lt;/code&gt; needed to be provided with a 
list of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Nuclei/wiki/Nuclei.Communication#communicationsubject&quot;&gt;communication subjects&lt;/a&gt; and a flag indicating if &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Nuclei/wiki/Nuclei.Communication#endpoints-and-their-discovery&quot;&gt;channel discovery&lt;/a&gt; was allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;cs&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; builder = &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; ContainerBuilder(); 
builder.RegisterModule(
    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; CommunicationModule(
        &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; List&amp;lt;CommunicationSubject&amp;gt;
            {
                CommunicationSubjects.Dataset,
            },
        &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;));&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In V0.6.5.0 an extra parameter needs to be provided which indicates which types of channel the communication layer is allowed to use to communicate with other instances. The allowable options are &lt;code&gt;ChannelType.NamedPipe&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ChannelType.TcpIP&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;cs&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; builder = &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; ContainerBuilder();
builder.RegisterModule(
    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; CommunicationModule(
        &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; List&amp;lt;CommunicationSubject&amp;gt;
            {
                CommunicationSubjects.Dataset,
            },
        &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;[]
            {
                ChannelType.NamedPipe,
                ChannelType.TcpIP,
            }, 
        &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;));&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>nRefs release - V0.1.0.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-25_nRefs-Release-v0100.html"/>
            <updated>2013-09-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-25_nRefs-Release-v0100.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/nRefs/releases/tag/v0.1.0.0&quot;&gt;first release&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/nRefs.html&quot;&gt;nRefs&lt;/a&gt; assembly reference extraction application has been released. This release&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The test output now includes an XML report with all the messages and an indication of test success or failure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Removed the Test data directory settings from the web service because test packages are now always dropped in the App_Data directory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>How this blog was created</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-25_How-this-blog-was-created.html"/>
            <updated>2013-09-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-25_How-this-blog-was-created.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A long time ago, in a location far, far, far away there was a hero in search for a quest ... &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And he searched ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And he searched .... &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And .. oh never mind, our hero he is not the object of this current post, thus we shall be leaving him in some weird limbo looking for his quest... oh well. The topic of this post is how this blog / website was build. It turns out that building anything in HTML, CSS, Node.js and all the other cool web technologies isn&amp;#39;t really my strong suit. However I&amp;#39;m hoping that the description of how I build this site may be useful to somebody at some point in time, if only to have a good laugh at my lack of CSS skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As much as I love writing code, the idea of writing my content in an angle bracket language didn&amp;#39;t really attract me so the plan was hatched (it came out of a purple egg, by the way) to write (nearly) all content in &lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; by using &lt;a href=&quot;http://docpad.org&quot;&gt;Docpad&lt;/a&gt;. Given that I&amp;#39;ve recently started using &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; for my open source projects why not use it for version control and GitHub pages to serve my website. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;#39;t bore you with the details on how to install Docpad, the Docpad website has an excellent introduction to all those things. Once the initial install is done Docpad allows you to create a skeleton website by executing the following command&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;dos&quot;&gt;Docpad run&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At which point Docpad presents a list of possible skeletons to use. In my case I selected the &lt;a href=&quot;http://html5boilerplate.com/&quot;&gt;HTML5 boilerplate template&lt;/a&gt;. In order to get a nice layout quickly I also used the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.freecsstemplates.org/previews/opentools/&quot;&gt;Open tools&lt;/a&gt; template. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I had the basic site layout sorted it was time to focus creating my own sections. Fortunately Docpad has a large number of plugins that provide useful additions to the generation process. For the generation of this site the following plugins are used:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/grassator/docpad-plugin-datefromfilename&quot;&gt;datefromfilename&lt;/a&gt; - Extracts the date of a post from the file name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docpad.org/plugin/gist/&quot;&gt;gist&lt;/a&gt; - Adds &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub gists&lt;/a&gt; to a page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docpad.org/plugin/highlightjs/&quot;&gt;highlightjs&lt;/a&gt; - Provides syntax highlighting for code samples. My current plan is to use this for the smaller samples and use GitHub gists for the larger ones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lucor/docpad-plugin-navlinks&quot;&gt;navlinks&lt;/a&gt; - Adds navigation links to the bottom of each post, pointing at the previous and next post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docpad.org/plugin/related/&quot;&gt;related&lt;/a&gt; - Allows you to find all related documents based on a given set of tags.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rantecki/docpad-plugin-tagging&quot;&gt;tagging&lt;/a&gt; - Generates the tag cloud for the sidebar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all the toys sorted it was time to integrate them in the templates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;menu&quot;&gt;Menu&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top level menu is based on a collection which contains all pages that have their &lt;code&gt;isPage&lt;/code&gt; flag set to &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;. Note that we also assume that these pages have 
the default layout. One thing to note is that the docpad.coffee configuration file seems to be sensitive to the type of whitespace you use. Either use spaces or tabs, but don&amp;#39;t mix them, otherwise you may get some weird errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src='https://gist.github.com/6375681.js?file=collections.pages.docpad.coffee'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the collection has been filled with pages it is used to create an unordered list with an additional highlight placed on the currently active page&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src='https://gist.github.com/6375681.js?file=menu.default.html'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sidebar&quot;&gt;Sidebar&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sidebar contains three different sections. The first section is the about section which is nothing special. The &lt;em&gt;recent&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;tags&lt;/em&gt; sections are more interesting from a website construction perspective. The &lt;em&gt;recent&lt;/em&gt; section based on the &lt;em&gt;frontpage&lt;/em&gt; collection which grabs all items from the posts and 
projects subdirectories and then sorts them by date. The &lt;em&gt;recent&lt;/em&gt; section only display the last 10 items in that collection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src='https://gist.github.com/6375681.js?file=recent.default.html'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;tags&lt;/em&gt; section is based on a collection provided by the tagging plugin. The font-size of the tag is based on the weight assigned to the tag by the tagging plugin. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src='https://gist.github.com/6375681.js?file=tags.default.html'&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;Each tag links to a page that contains all the posts that contain that tag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;projects-tag-indexes-and-posts&quot;&gt;Projects, tag indexes and posts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project pages all have a shared layout which provides them with a title and a section that lists all the posts tagged with the name of the project&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src='https://gist.github.com/6375681.js?file=project-linkedposts.html'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posts are displayed in three different places: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The home page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tag index page, containing all posts with a given tag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The post page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All pages use the same partial layout file in order to display the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src='https://gist.github.com/6375681.js?file=post-content.html'&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;The only difference between the post page and the other pages is that the post page will display all the comments. The comment system is based on
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ivanzuzak.info/2011/02/18/github-hosted-comments-for-github-hosted-blogs.html&quot;&gt;comments on a GitHub issue&lt;/a&gt; and uses a small amount of Javascript to pull the comments across into the comment list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src='https://gist.github.com/6375681.js?file=post.html'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&quot;acknowledgements-&quot;&gt;Acknowledgements:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally there some people that have provided some descriptions of how their own blogs were created with Docpad (or other static generators). Below are the posts that I used to assemble my own blog. A big thank you to the original posters!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ivanzuzak.info/2011/02/18/github-hosted-comments-for-github-hosted-blogs.html&quot;&gt;Ivan Zuzak&lt;/a&gt; for his post describing how to use GitHub issues as a way to provide comments on a blog post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://takitapart.com&quot;&gt;takitapart&lt;/a&gt; provided an &lt;a href=&quot;http://takitapart.com/posts/organizing-docpad/&quot;&gt;excellent&lt;/a&gt; post describing how to organise content in a Docpad website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lucor.github.io&quot;&gt;Luca&amp;#39;s forge&lt;/a&gt; provided a good start to using Docpad in his &lt;a href=&quot;http://lucor.github.io/post/migrating-from-octopress-to-docpad/&quot;&gt;migration&lt;/a&gt; post. This site also provides some very nice ideas around the way posts and tags should look.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.delarre.net&quot;&gt;Ben Delarre&lt;/a&gt; provided a nice &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.delarre.net/posts/blogging-with-docpad/&quot;&gt;summary&lt;/a&gt; of his own Docpad setup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Sherlock release - V0.4.4.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-21_Sherlock-Release-v0440.html"/>
            <updated>2013-09-21T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-21_Sherlock-Release-v0440.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/releases/tag/v0.4.4.0&quot;&gt;V0.4.4.0&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/sherlock.html&quot;&gt;Sherlock&lt;/a&gt; regression testing application has been released. This release provides two improvements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The test output now includes an XML report with all the messages and an indication of test success or failure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Removed the Test data directory settings from the web service because test packages are now always dropped in the App_Data directory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>PG2 - Second day</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-16_PG2-Second-day-flying.html"/>
            <updated>2013-09-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-16_PG2-Second-day-flying.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Sunday the weather was good enough for some flying on the west coast. So at 11.30am about 8 of us gathered at &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kariotahi_Beach&quot;&gt;Kario&lt;/a&gt; and the second day of my &lt;a href=&quot;/tags/PG2.html&quot;&gt;PG2&lt;/a&gt; had started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&quot;left&quot; alt=&quot;Paraglider soaring high over beautiful west coast&quot; src=&quot;/images/paragliding/paraglide_0004.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing to notice about the west coast is that it looks amazing, rugged and empty. It seems that with paragliding besides the flying I also get to look out over the amazing landscapes New Zealand has. Double win!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before I get to fly as a qualified pilot a lot more training has to be had and that we did. The day started off with some ground handling exercises on the really old gliders. My first taste of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paragliding#Reverse_launch&quot;&gt;reverse launching&lt;/a&gt; except with out the actual turning around and flying bit. It turns out reverse launching isn&amp;#39;t actually as simple as I thought it would be. Having flown kites for many years I thought I would get the reverse launch down pretty easily but when the gliders get larger and the controls are reversed things get difficult. More practise is required ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the ground handling a few short flights down the slope were made with a larger glider to practise the forward starts and then it was time to get some actual flights done. I managed to get three short flights in where I got to practise forward starts, turning and then landing. Some observations (which are probably obvious to those that have flown paragliders before): &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If there is a distinct edge at the end of the start field then when you fly out over that edge the glider will climb rapidly due to the wind blasting straight up the edge. This is nothing to worry about, although it feels slightly disconcerting at first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A paraglider moves around more than you would think, even in a nice constant sea breeze&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you land at even a slight angle to the wind it gets really hard to put the glider on its back, instead of its side. I got only one landing totally right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&quot;right&quot; alt=&quot;Flying my new Gin Atlas&quot; src=&quot;/images/paragliding/paraglide_0005.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then it was time for the unexpected highlight of the day. When I paid for the PG2 course I paid for a combination package, which includes the PG2 course, a glider and a harness. Now I still haven&amp;#39;t selected a harness but I have selected the glider, a bright red &lt;a href=&quot;http://gingliders.com/paragliders/atlas/&quot;&gt;Gin Atlas&lt;/a&gt;. I didn&amp;#39;t expect to be able to fly it so soon in my course but after my initial three flights both instructors gave me the go ahead to fly it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I managed a further two flights with it. The first one was a nice long soaring flight where I got to get a feel for the glider. At the end of the flight I managed to get quite a bit of height. And to top that flight off the instructor guided me in for a top landing upon which I nearly broke my glider by stuffing up the landing. Fortunately no gliders or pilots where hurt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last flight of the day was back down to the beach to pack our equipment and drive home. I set myself up for a landing approach and promptly overshot my selected landing spot by about 100 meters or so. I guess selecting and landing in the right spot is yet another skill I have to work on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all it was an amazing day of flying, especially the nice soaring flight on my shiny new glider.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Sherlock release - V0.4.3.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-14_Sherlock-Release-v0430.html"/>
            <updated>2013-09-14T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-14_Sherlock-Release-v0430.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/releases/tag/v0.4.3.0&quot;&gt;V0.4.3.0&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/sherlock.html&quot;&gt;Sherlock&lt;/a&gt; regression testing application has been released. This release provides several bug fixes for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The console application: Changed the way the REST URLs are constructed so that it works if the web service on a sub-part of a domain, e.g. &lt;code&gt;http://myserver/sherlock&lt;/code&gt; works now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The web service: Added Trace.Write statements for ease of debugging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The windows service: Fixed a dead-lock bug in the shut-down process and linked all processes via a Windows Job Object to ensure that all child processes are terminated if the service is terminated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Sherlock release - V0.4.2.0</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-11_Sherlock-Release-v0420.html"/>
            <updated>2013-09-11T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-11_Sherlock-Release-v0420.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/releases/tag/v0.4.2.0&quot;&gt;V0.4.2.0&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/sherlock.html&quot;&gt;Sherlock&lt;/a&gt; regression testing application has been released. This release adds one bug fix and one improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bug fix is a change to the &lt;code&gt;IsHyperVMachine&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;IsPhysicalMachine&lt;/code&gt; stored procedures in order to make them easier to use correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The improvement is the addition of build steps that package the web projects into a ZIP file for easier deployment. These zip files can now also be retrieved from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/releases/tag/v0.4.2.0&quot;&gt;release note&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Sherlock release - V0.4.0.1</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-08_Sherlock-Release-v0401.html"/>
            <updated>2013-09-08T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-08_Sherlock-Release-v0401.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Version &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pvandervelde/Sherlock/releases/tag/v0.4.0.1&quot;&gt;V0.4.0.1&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/sherlock.html&quot;&gt;Sherlock&lt;/a&gt; regression testing application has been released. This release adds two new features and one improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new features are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ability to continue with a test sequence after a test step has failed. The test step should indicate that the failure mode is &amp;#39;continue&amp;#39;. Other option is &amp;#39;stop&amp;#39;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added a test step that allows executing a console application with a set of input parameters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following gist gives an overview of what the configuration for the new console test step looks like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src='https://gist.github.com/6483292.js'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The improvement is in the HTML output report which is has been overhauled to improve the layout and readability.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>First time paragliding</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-03_First-time-paragliding.html"/>
            <updated>2013-09-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-09-03_First-time-paragliding.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A little while ago I signed up for a &lt;a href=&quot;http://paraglidingnewzealand.com/information/learning-to-fly&quot;&gt;PG2&lt;/a&gt; paragliding course 
with &lt;a href=&quot;http://wingsandwaves.co.nz&quot;&gt;Wings and Waves&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately I signed up just before winter crept in and made it impossible to fly. As
we are moving towards spring the weather has been getting better and last Sunday the weather was good enough for us (my girlfriend and me) to
have our first shot at flying a paraglider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&quot;left&quot; alt=&quot;Casey ground handling the old glider&quot; src=&quot;/images/paragliding/paraglide_0001.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So on Sunday morning we met up with the Wings and Waves crew and drove over to a nice, if some what soggy, hill somewhere around Pukemore, south of the Bombay hills for the first steps of our training. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first part consisted of learning how to ground handle a paraglider. Ground handling is the art of controlling the paraglider while on the ground. This turns out to be harder than it first looks. In the air the pilot will normally be centred underneath the paraglider. On the ground however the pilot may not be directly below the paraglider which means the pilot needs to actively move around to keep the paraglider above them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&quot;right&quot; alt=&quot;Me doing a forward start with the old glider&quot; src=&quot;/images/paragliding/paraglide_0002.JPG&quot; /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we got the hang of the ground handling we started learning forwards starts, or alpine starts. With this method of starting you face forward with the glider behind you. Once you have sorted out the lines you move forwards until the lines are tensioned and then you run at a constant pace. The first glider we used was the really old one we used in ground handling. Given that it was not very large it was pretty easy to run with, and running we did, lots of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we got a few good runs in with the old glider the instructor found us a more modern paraglider to play with. This one was considerably larger and far more interesting. Over the remainder of the day we slowly worked our way up the hill, starting from a higher position each time, and being rewarded with a little more flight time and a little more height each time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&quot;left&quot; alt=&quot;Casey having a little flight with the newer glider&quot; src=&quot;/images/paragliding/paraglide_0003.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the beginning both my girl friend and me got to use the same glider but it turns out I&amp;#39;ve got a big fat ass and so I had to upgrade to bigger gliders a few more times. Each time being reminded that bigger gliders also mean more backwards pull on start and higher flights. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all it was a good day flying. I still have a lot of work to do on all parts of my launching and flying skills (obviously given that this is the first time), but the one thing I really noticed I need to work on is distance estimation and flare timing. I got that wrong a few times and it was fortunate that the landing area was soggy because it made for nice, if what splashy, landings even if I miscalculated my flare timing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all a good time was had by all and we are definitely keen for more flying. Hopefully with less running and more flying next time.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Why this blog was created</title>
            <link href="http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-08-30_Why-this-blog-was-created.html"/>
            <updated>2013-08-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://pvandervelde.github.io/posts/2013-08-30_Why-this-blog-was-created.html</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago I had a blog on Blogger but that never got further than a few posts, mainly because I ran out of interesting topics to write about. That
and my &lt;a href=&quot;/about.html&quot;&gt;studies&lt;/a&gt; started interfering with life in general ... it seems research does that to ones life. In any case the old blog stalled and no
more posts were written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I have been wanting to improve my writing skills, you see, as software engineer I&amp;#39;m reasonably good at writing instructions for a three year
old, eh I mean a computer, but I am not particularly good at writing concise human-friendly text. I have written two dissertations, one for my master degree
and one for my PhD, but neither of those qualify as either concise or human-friendly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that the only way to get better at writing is to practise, practise and practise some more, I thought writing posts about things that interest me
would be a good way to improve my writing skills. And on top of that it may help me improve my skills in explaining technical constructs as well. Double win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only thing left to answer is what shall I be writing about. Well obviously those things that interest me, mostly being:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My open source &lt;a href=&quot;/projects.html&quot;&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt;. All of them could do with some additional documentation and maybe even some examples. I guess having a 
blog is just an additional reason to finally write those&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All the (exciting) things I get up to when rock climbing or paragliding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And if things progress nicely I might write some articles describing some work I am doing at the moment that is a continuation of the software
development I did for my PhD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
</feed>